Register of the Archbishop Apollinarii (Koshevoi) papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Archbishop Apollinarii (Koshevoi) papers
1874-1935
2008C43
Hoover Institution Archives
2 microfilm reels (0.3 linear feet)
Diaries, correspondence, and speeches and writings, relating to the Russian Orthodox Church and to Russian émigré affairs.
Apollinarii, Abp. of North America and Canada, 1874-1933.
Access
The collection is open for research
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Alternative Forms of Material Available
A portion of the collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Original Materials
Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Chronology
1874 October 16 Born, Valok, Poltava guberniia, Russia
1888 Graduated, Romenskoe dukhovnoe uchilishche
1894 Graduated, Poltavskaia dukhovnaia seminariia
1898 Tonsured monk and ordained hierodeacon
1905 Graduated, Kievskaia dukhovnaia akademiia
1917 Ordained bishop of Belgorod
1922 Sent to Jerusalem to oversee the Russian Ecclesiastical Mission
1924 Arrives in New York, Bishop of Winnipeg
1927 Bishop of North America and San Francisco
1929 Archbishop of North America and Canada
1933 June 19 Died, New York, NY
1965 Reburial, Holy Trinity Monastery, Jordanville, NY
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers reflect the ecclesiastical career path of Archbishop Apollinarii (Koshevoi), beginning with his educational formation in pre-Revolutionary Russia to emigration, first in Serbia, then Jerusalem, Palestine, and, finally, as Archbishop of North America and Canada. His assignments, both in Jerusalem and North America, coincided with difficult jurisdictional controversies, especially on the North American continent. His Correspondence reveals a lively exchange with both clergy and parishioners in the U.S. and Canada, and includes directives, ukazy, and ecclesiastical documents forwarded to him from the ecclesiastical administration of the Russian Orthodox Church Outside Russia in Belgrade, Serbia.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Holy Trinity Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series: Biographical file, Diaries, Correspondence, Speeches and writings, Russian Ecclesiastical Mission File, and Printed matter
Biography
Andrei Vasil’evich Koshevoi was born in Valok, Russia, in the Poltava guberniia, on October 16, 1874. He grew up in a pious Russian Orthodox family, went through the traditional theological education, graduating from the Romenskoe dukhovnoe uchilishche in 1888 and the Poltavskaia dukhovnaia seminariia in 1894. Early on, Koshevoi chose his path, and in 1898 he was tonsured a monk by his spiritual mentor Archbishop Antonii (Khrapovitskii), given the name Apollinarii, and subsequently ordained. He then continued his education at the famous Kievskaia dukhovnaia akademiia, graduating in 1905.
In 1917, Apollinarii (Koshevoi) was consecrated bishop of Belgorod, having spent the preceding years teaching and carrying out administrative functions at theological institutions. Archbishop Apollinarii arrived in Serbia in 1920, as a result of the Russian Revolution, and was sent to Jerusalem in 1922 to oversee the activities of the Russian Ecclesiastical Mission. Two years later, he arrived in New York, having been assigned as vicar bishop to Metropolitan Platon (Rozhdestvenskii). Although his time in the United States coincided with difficult jurisdictional controversies, he played an important role in the formation of Russian Orthodox parishes there. From 1929 to 1933, he was archbishop of North America and Canada; he died in New York in 1933.
Russia--Emigration and immigration.; Russians--Canada.; Russians--United States.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'.
- Biographical File, 1874-1935. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes anniversary addresses, awards, biographical sketches, certificates (birth, citizenship, medical, Mutual Aid Fund), ecclesiastical and educational documents, estate documents, farewell address, memorial service announcement, materials related to the erection of a memorial to Archbishop Apollinarii, and passports. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Addresses on the occasion of the 15th anniversary of Archbishop Apollinarii's episcopacy, 1932 (Folder 1: 1-2)
  - Awards, 1914-1933 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Biographical sketches, 1928 and undated. (Folder 1: 4)
    Typescripts and printed copy
  - Certificates, 1874-1933
    - Birth, 1874 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Citizenship, 1933 (Folder 1: 6)
    - Medical, 1921 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Mutual Aid Fund, 1933 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Ecclesiastical documents, 1900-1927 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Educational documents, 1894-1917. (Folder 1: 10)
  - Estate documents, 1934-1937 and undated (Folder 1: 11)
  - Farewell address, 1926. (Folder 1: 12)
    Holograph
  - Memorial service announcement, 1936 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Memorial to Archbishop Apollinarii, 1933-1935 and undated (Folder 1: 14)
  - Passports, 1917-1933 (Folder 1: 15)
- Diaries, 1912-1928 (Folder 1: 16)
- Correspondence, 1920-1934. (Box 2)
  Letters and ecclesiastical documents, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - General, 1927-1931 and undated (Folder 2: 1)
    - Addresses of clergy, 1925 and undated (Folder 2: 2)
    - Log of outgoing correspondence, 1927-1930 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Unidentified, 1925-1932 and undated (Folder 2: 4)
  - Adam (Filippovskii), Archbishop, 1931 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Aleksandrov, Elena and Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1929-1931. (Folder 2: 6)
    Includes printed copy of open letter by Elena Aleksandrov to Russian clergy in North America
  - Anastasii (Gribanovskii), Archbishop (later – Metropolitan), undated (Folder 2: 7)
  - Antonin, Arkhimandrit, 1927 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Barskii, Konstantin, undated (Folder 2: 9)
  - Bekkarevich, Boris, 1932 and undated. (Folder 2: 10)
    Includes documents relating to the purchase of land for a proposed monastery
  - Bogoiavlenskii, N., 1927 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Borzov, N., 1926 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Feodosii (Samoilovich), Bishop, 1926-1932 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Feofil (Pashkovskii), Bishop, 1925 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Gornii convent, Jerusalem, 1924 and undated (Folder 2: 15)
  - Ioasaf (Skorodumov), Bishop, 1931 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Kruglov, A., 1932 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Krupenskii, Aleksandr Nikolaevich, 1928-1932 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Kulibin, Vladimir K., 1927 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Lakhno, Ignatii, Reverend, 1930 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Turkevich, Leonid, Reverend (later – Metropolitan Leontii), 1925-1926 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Mikhail (Zeikan), Hieromonk, undated (Folder 2: 22)
  - Mitropol'skii, Nikolai, Reverend, 1926 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Nikolai (Karpov), Bishop, 1931-1932 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Platon (Rozhdestvenskii), Metropolitan, 1922-1927 and undated (Folder 2: 25)
  - Russian Church Assistance Fund, 1927 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Seniuk, Vasilii A., 1929-1930 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Simeon (Nabrekov), Archimandrite, 1932 (Folder 2: 28)
  - Simon (Vinogradov), Archbishop, 1932 (Folder 2: 29)
  - Smirnov, N., 1928 (Folder 2: 30)
  - St. Peter and Paul Church, 1928 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Synod of Bishops of the Russian Orthodox Church Outside Russia.
    Includes documents signed by Metropolitan Antonii (Khrapovitskii), Iu. G. Grabbe, and E. I. Makharablidze
    - General
      - 1920-1928 and undated (Folder 3: 2)
      - 1930-1932 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Ukazy, 1922-1933 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Telep, Ioann, Reverend, 1925 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Tikhon, Bishop, undated (Folder 3: 6)
  - Turin, Ivan Arsen'evich, 1930-1931 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Vadkovskii, Vasilii Vasil'evich, 1934 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Vdovichenko, Petr, Reverend, 1930-1931 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Vinall, G.H., 1925 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Vitalii (Maksimenko), Archimandrite (later – Archbishop), 1932 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Zagorskii, Mr. and Mrs., 1927 (Folder 3: 12)
- Speeches and Writings, 1927-1932 and undated.
  Appeals, epistles, pamphlet, speeches, arranged chronologically by title
  - General - Epistles and appeals, 1927-1932. (Folder 3: 13)
    Printed copies
  - Untitled speech on ecclesiastical governance, undated. (Folder 3: 14)
  - "Istina da vostorzhestvuet,", 1928. (Folder 3: 15)
    Printed copy
- Russian Ecclesiastical Mission File, 1921-1923. (Folder 3: 16)
  Accounts of the activities of the Russian Ecclesiastical Mission in Jerusalem. Includes a financial account of the mission's activities for the year 1921, and an account of the first Arab Orthodox gathering in 1923. Holographs arranged chronologically
- Printed Matter, 1919-1933 and undated.
  Clippings, leaflets, and brochures, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Clippings, 1930-1933 and undated (Folder 3: 17)
  - Leaflets, undated (Folder 3: 18)
  - Olsuf'ev, Dimitrii Adamovich, Mysli soborianina o nashei tserkovnoi smutie, 1928. (Folder 3: 19)
  - Zhurnal trudov tserkovno-narodnogo sobora, 1919. (Folder 3: 20)